Hi, I'm Anna,
and I'm an engineer on
the UI Frameworks team.
And I'm Maria,
a Human Interface Designer
working on Apple's design system.
Wait, why am I here?
Every designer is an engineer,
and every engineer is a designer.
You need to understand
both to build a great app.
Today, Anna and I are
going to teach you
how to raise the bar for
your bars on iPhone Duo.
iPhone Duo is Apple's
first multi-display iPhone,
giving people the freedom to use it
in the way that feels
right for the moment.
And you'll notice right
away, it's different,
introducing a new,
distinct silhouette.
And that shape matters.
The wider aspect ratio gives your apps
more horizontal space to work with.
To make the most out of that width and
preserve vertical space for content,
controls that normally
sit at the top and bottom,
move to the side,
where they're also easier to reach.
This new design maximizes space
for vertical content
on the outer display.
And their position remains consistent
when you open iPhone Duo to the
inner display and landscape.
But as you open the
device in portrait,
the larger display returns
to a familiar iPhone layout
with horizontal bars.
And remember, these are
the same components,
just adapted to a different layout.
Now that you understand
the principles behind it,
here are a few things to keep in mind
when designing and implementing
great bar experiences on iPhone Duo.
First, we'll help you
orient to a new axis
and take your bars
vertical on iPhone Duo.
Next, we'll discuss item ordering
and how it interacts with
different containers.
After that, we'll share how
you can tailor toolbar content
for a vertical axis.
Finally, we'll highlight how
to manage the overflow menu.
But Anna, before we get into that,
can I show you the app that
I've been working on? Totally.
So I've already done the
work to make it resizable.
However, my bars are still horizontal.
Am I missing something?
I got you, Maria.
To opt your app into
the new bar behavior,
there are a few things
you'll need to do.
First,
rebuild your app
against the latest SDKs.
Now Maria's app is
ready for iPhone Duo.
For more details
on what other behaviors are
enabled when you rebuild,
check out "Prepare Your App
for iPhone Duo."
Next, make sure you're using
the bars provided by
navigation containers
like TabView
or NavigationStack.
In SwiftUI,
pair the toolbar
modifier with containers
like NavigationStack
or NavigationSplitView.
In UIKit, prefer using
UINavigationController and
UITabBarController,
which manage their own bars.
For example, set toolbar
items on a view controller
and place it into a
navigation controller
rather than creating
a custom UIToolbar.
When used to build custom bars,
content from sub-components
like UIToolbar,
UINavigationBar,
or UITabBar won't be considered.
Now that you know how to allow bars
to move vertically in your app,
I'm going to dive deeper into
how their content is placed.
iPhone Duo allows navigation, toolbar,
and tab bar controls to
coexist within a shared region.
A helpful way to think
about it is to imagine
rotating 90 degrees
into a vertical stack.
Depending on your layout,
it may contain
different combinations of these items.
Here in Notes,
the layout uses a toolbar,
while in Clock,
the layout includes a tab bar.
And in Fitness, the layout uses
both a toolbar and a tab bar.
In more complex layouts, toolbar items
can only move vertically
when their container
is positioned along the display edge.
In split views, only the
detail column participates.
Items from other columns
remain horizontal.
And since detail columns
already have a vertical bar,
inspectors don't receive their own
when expanded to avoid confusion.
On the outer display, if your
sheets already have a toolbar,
it's displayed vertically.
On the inner display,
they're centered by default,
and items remain horizontal.
When you use the
preferredPlacement API
to change their position,
sheets placed on the left
remain without a vertical bar,
while sheets placed on
the right receive one.
And because the bar is
aligned with the hardware,
it stays on the same
side of the device
in right-to-left languages.
The content adapts around it while
the bar itself remains fixed.
In summary, while it might be tempting
to change the axis
for all your controls,
keep them associated
with their container.
When displayed vertically,
items retain
a clear top-to-bottom hierarchy.
Start by auditing your
existing toolbar configuration,
making sure that controls
follow the recommended order.
Reserve the top for primary
navigation controls,
like back or close, followed by
prominent actions, such as done.
If you're using a
navigation controller,
the back button is
added automatically.
For custom back or close buttons,
use cancellationAction
placement in SwiftUI.
And in UIKit,
use a leading item and make sure
leftItemSupplementsBackButton
is set to false,
which is the default.
leftItemSupplementsBackButton?
Who named that API?
Wasn't me.
For prominent actions,
place them using topBarPinnedTrailing
placement in SwiftUI
or pinnedTrailingGroup
in UIKit.
Remaining items preserve
their original grouping
with a vertical spacer
visually separating top
and bottom placements even
when unified into a single bar.
And remember, not every pose
lays out bars vertically.
Keep control placement
consistent so people
don't have to relearn
where actions live
as they use iPhone Duo.
Now that you know
where items are placed,
let's make sure your
toolbar content is ready.
You may be familiar with bars that
lay out your items horizontally.
Now, iPhone Duo turns
that on its side.
Unlike horizontal bars,
where items have a fixed height
and allow flexible item width,
vertical ones
allow flexible item height
and have a fixed width.
This makes vertical bars better suited
for symbol-only item representations.
Typically,
your app specifies two pieces
of data on your toolbar content,
an icon and a title.
Depending on the context and
what's specified on the item,
the system then chooses
what representation to show.
When items are visible in the
existing top and bottom bars,
they prefer showing the icon,
like the share button here.
If there's no icon,
like the edit button,
they show the text.
When items move into
the overflow menu,
they show both the title and the icon.
None of this is changing
with vertical bars.
You still specify the same content
and place the same items
into a horizontal bar.
The difference is the system now also
considers whether your
content is better suited
to be on a vertical
or horizontal axis.
Items with an icon,
like the back and share buttons,
change their axis to be vertical.
And text-only items,
like the edit button,
continue to stay on
the horizontal axis.
If you're already setting
the title and image
by using a SwiftUI label
or the properties on UIBarButtonItem,
you're well on your way to
getting ready for vertical bars.
In general,
you want to provide all the
information about your items up front
and let the system pick the right
representation for the context.
This means that even if
your content is an image,
it's still important
to provide a title.
Just like for horizontal bars,
the system uses it whenever an item
moves into an overflow
menu or an expanded form.
By default, SwiftUI and UIKit
infer where to place the
item based on its content,
like if it's an item that's text only
or a symbol in text.
If you need to adjust
this default behavior,
there's a new AxisBehavior API.
You use it in a few
different situations.
Related items should
stay on the same axis.
One common instance is
an item that transitions
between a symbol and a text,
like this edit button in Clock.
That item shouldn't be
placed in a vertical bar,
even though the symbol
could theoretically
be displayed vertically.
If you're using the system
edit button, you're all set.
It stays in the horizontal
bar automatically.
If you're creating a custom item
that transitions between
a symbol and a text,
use the horizontal-only axis behavior
like this custom select button does.
On the other hand,
if your view is a custom view
in UIKit or a complex view,
the system keeps it horizontal.
If your custom view does support
a vertical representation,
like the compass view
in the top right,
set the vertical-preferred
axis behavior
to allow it to go into a vertical bar.
Minimize title-only items
or custom views that show
both text
and an image so more
content can go vertical.
In most situations,
these are good candidates
to use their symbol representation.
For example, rather than
keeping the count inline,
I can use a badge on the inbox
to turn an item that displays
both text and a symbol
into a symbol-only item
that feels at home in a vertical bar.
If you aren't already
using the badge API
added in iOS 26, adopt it to get
a system-standard badge appearance
on all devices.
A helpful way to evaluate
whether a custom view needs text
is to ask: is it simply
reinforcing the symbol,
or does it
carry standalone information?
If the text is just supplementary,
the symbol alone will clearly
communicate the action.
However, if the text does
contain meaningful information,
like a cart button
displaying a dollar amount,
it's better to keep the control
in the horizontal bar.
Lastly, accessory bars should
remain attached to keyboard
rather than moving
to the vertical axis.
Custom views require a bit more work
to get them ready to
be laid out vertically.
When you opt items in,
make sure they either
fit the bar's fixed width or
have a vertically adapted layout.
Consider if any metric
should be adjusted
for the vertical representation.
For example, this custom
action panel hides its titles
and becomes slightly
shorter when vertical
to allow more room for other content.
For custom views in particular,
you might want to make changes
when a vertical bar is present.
To know that, read the
toolbarVerticalEdge
environment property or trait.
You can read it within content view
or inside your item's custom view.
The value is populated when
items can be on vertical axis,
and nil or unspecified
when they can't.
Just like horizontal
bars, a vertical bar
doesn't have a scroll-edge
effect by default.
However, it does have a background
when the reduced transparency
accessibility setting is enabled.
Make sure your custom
view content stays legible regardless.
By default, flexible
spacers are zero size
in the vertical axis.
But fixed spacers continue to
respect their minimum size.
Your app shouldn't be
creating additional spacing,
regardless of if a bar is
horizontal or vertical.
Maria,
didn't you talk about this
in your video for WWDC25?
Yes, I did.
Thanks for watching.
If your app hasn't already
updated its bars to the new design
or grouped individual
items along leading
and trailing edges,
now's the perfect time.
Lastly, let's talk
about managing overflow.
On the outer display in landscape,
items overflow more often
simply because there's
less vertical space.
The bar may also need to overflow
as other competing UI appears,
like the keyboard or
when using Picture
in Picture in open portrait.
The first decision is which
should stay visible longer,
your toolbar items or your tab bar.
In navigation-focused experiences,
like this Podcasts view,
the toolbar compresses first,
so primary destinations
remain accessible.
This is the default behavior.
In task-oriented experiences,
like this view from the Games app,
the tab bar compresses first
to preserve frequently
accessed actions.
Use the toolbarCompressionBehavior API
to configure your app's
preference for each view.
From there, toolbars need a
little more consideration.
With more items to manage,
you'll also need to
prioritize what stays visible.
If your app already has its own
overflow, consolidate its actions
into a single system-managed menu.
You can do that using
ToolbarOverflowMenu in SwiftUI
or additionalOverflowItems in UIKit.
And not every existing menu
should become an overflow.
The ellipsis is the standard
overflow symbol on iPhone.
Reserve it for that purpose
rather than introducing
symbols from other platforms,
and give other menus
a distinct symbol.
To keep the right content
visible for longer,
make sure to express your
preferences to the system.
If you've prioritized the tab bar
or your toolbar exceeds
the available space,
items will begin moving
into the overflow menu.
Toolbar visibility priority
gives you fine-grained control
over which ones remain visible.
By default, items overflow
from bottom to top,
but you can also assign
each item a high,
low, or custom priority
to control the order
in which they collapse.
Within your items, start
giving priority by groups.
Then prioritize items within
each one if you need to.
Use visibilityPriority APIs
in SwiftUI and UIKit
to configure this priority.
And check out what's new in
SwiftUI from WWDC26 to learn more.
When assigning visibility priorities,
think about what items people
need to access most often.
Frequently used actions
like Compose in Mail
or New Note in Notes
should be amongst the last
to move into overflow.
Likewise, controls that
convey important status,
such as items with badges,
should remain visible for longer
to preserve glanceability.
Maria, I get why bars are
laid out vertically now,
but should they be
vertical everywhere?
Most apps are good candidates.
However, there are a
few cases where your app
may want to disable this behavior.
If your app is a single-page
app with a bottom-heavy layout
like Calculator, consider
if a horizontal layout
might allow the content
to fully expand.
Similarly, if a sheet is control-heavy
with only one item,
like the close button here,
consider disabling a vertical
bar so it doesn't reduce
available space.
Use the toolbarVerticalBehavior
and preferredVerticalBarBehavior APIs
to disable this.
It started with a
pretty simple question.
What if bars didn't have to
be at the top and the bottom?
Spoiler, they moved.
To the side.
Not that far.
It keeps the content feeling spacious
while keeping controls accessible.
The same familiar experience
made for an entirely new iPhone.
To get your app ready, the first step
is building your app
with the latest SDKs.
Audit the bars in your app and ensure
that they're ready for the new design.
Update any custom items so they're
ready to be placed vertically.
And make sure to assign
overflow priorities
so the system can adapt.
Anything else?
It's in the overflow menu.
See you soon!